<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Personal on Ugur&#39;s Personal Documentation</title>
    <link>https://blog.ugurelveren.com/categories/personal/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Personal on Ugur&#39;s Personal Documentation</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://blog.ugurelveren.com/categories/personal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>I Moved My Blog to GitHub Again</title>
      <link>https://blog.ugurelveren.com/post/i-have-done-something/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.ugurelveren.com/post/i-have-done-something/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve done something.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Again.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My cat is on my lap, I&amp;rsquo;m listening to music with my headset, and I&amp;rsquo;m writing a blog post about how I moved my blog to another platform. Well, not another platform, actually. I moved it to old friend GitHub again.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This time, though, I developed something simple so I can manage my blog with my own solution.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;starting-from-the-beginning&#34;&gt;Starting From the Beginning&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What was the previous platform I was using? I was using Write.as. It&amp;rsquo;s a simple platform where you can share your posts on the Fediverse. The UI is minimal, and the main goal of the CMS platform is clear: just write and share your articles.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Casual Exploration of Ingredient Awareness and Global Food Regulations</title>
      <link>https://blog.ugurelveren.com/post/ingredient-awareness/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.ugurelveren.com/post/ingredient-awareness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I often find my mind wandering to different topics, interrupting phone calls, meetings, or reading sessions. These thoughts take center stage, making it challenging to refocus on the original task.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, this mental game sometimes proves helpful. Whether it&amp;rsquo;s a forgotten task during a book or a work-related bug that surfaces while spending time with family, these moments can be both distracting and beneficial.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A peculiar incident occurred last week when, despite my usual preference for organic food, I accidentally purchased non-organic sourdough bread. Initially trying to ignore it after enjoying a slice for breakfast, curiosity led me to search for its ingredients. The search took me down a rabbit hole of articles and comparisons between the European Union and the United States, accompanied by alarming posters like &amp;ldquo;Stop Eating Cancer.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Battling Mosquitoes: A Personal Journey</title>
      <link>https://blog.ugurelveren.com/post/battling-mosquitoes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.ugurelveren.com/post/battling-mosquitoes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In late August, southern California faced a mosquito invasion. These tiny pests seemed to appear out of nowhere, leaving their itchy marks on unsuspecting victims. Whether you had a bug screen or not, they found their way into your home, and you&amp;rsquo;d wake up with irritating mosquito bites. At first, you might not notice them, but as time passed, the incessant itching would become undeniable.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;These mosquitoes were notorious for targeting ankles, leaving small, pink, and itchy bites. Sometimes, you&amp;rsquo;d wake up with not just one or two but possibly three or more bites. The constant itching would make you want to scratch your ankles, especially when walking. It was nearly impossible to scratch them all the time, like when driving, where you&amp;rsquo;d long for relief.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Goodbye HashNode, Welcome Writefreely</title>
      <link>https://blog.ugurelveren.com/post/goodbye-hashnode-welcome-writefreely/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://blog.ugurelveren.com/post/goodbye-hashnode-welcome-writefreely/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since the beginning of the pandemic, I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed a repetitive pattern of content on the internet across various platforms. Whether it&amp;rsquo;s on Reddit, different social media sites, or news websites and popular blogs, the same or similar content keeps circulating. Additionally, Google searches have taken a peculiar turn. When searching in English, the results often differ from the same websites, and in other languages like Turkish, you might encounter clickbait websites with strong SEO but weak content.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
